Guide to the Florence Ledyard Cross Kitchelt papers, 1896-1954.
Kitchelt, Florence Ledyard Cross papers, 1896-1954.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Florence Ledyard Cross Kitchelt papers, 1896-1954, 1898-1910 (bulk)
2009
Florence Ledyard Cross Kitchelt, 1874-1961.
26 items.
Correspondence, notes, reminiscences, and printed items.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Letters from Susan Dixwell Miller (Mrs. Gerrit Smith Miller) concerning Miss Cross' settlement house work for women in Brooklyn; letters, notes, and reminiscences concerning the beginnings of the George Junior Republic in Freeville, New York; and family letters and printed items.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Letters from Susan Dixwell Miller (Mrs. Gerrit Smith Miller) concerning Miss Cross' settlement house work for women in Brooklyn; letters, notes, and reminiscences concerning the beginnings of the George Junior Republic in Freeville, New York; and family letters and printed items.
In Mss. file, Box 51.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kitchelt, Florence Ledyard Cross, 1874-1961.; Miller, Susan Dixwell, 1845-1924.; George Junior Republic (Freeville, N. Y.)
Subjects:
Social settlements.; Poor women.
Places:
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)--Poor.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence
  - Mrs. F.H. Cross, Rochester, Aug. 15, 1898, to daughter, Florence, who had just gone to the George Junior Republic as a volunteer worker; family matters, a few inquiries re: GJR. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - J. W. Jenks, Dept. of Political Science, Cornell, to FLC at GJR, Dec. 8, 1898 re: choice of teacher for primary department. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Father to FLC, from Rochester, Jan. 16, 1899, concerning a recent fire in FLC's cottage at GJR. Also, brief note from Mother; references to a Miss Anthony [Susan B.?]. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (2 pcs.) from Florence, GJR, Feb. 5, 1899, to "My very dear girls," [Wells College], describing beginnings, aims, facilities of the GJR and her own work with the children. [FLC left in 1900.] (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letters (3 pcs.) from B.G. ["Best Girl" - Susan Dixwell Miller (Mrs. Gerrit Smith Miller)], Geneva, N.Y., to "Dear My Girl" [Florence], Feb. 10, 1904, praises recipience for giving up other plans for a life of service in settlement work; discusses personal matters. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (3 pcs.) from Susan Dixwell Miller, Peterboro, N.Y. to Florence, Apr. 27, 1905, advising and encouraging her in her settlement work; mentions former GJR students, Jacob Smith and William Seidell. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (2 pcs.), Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Aug. 25, 1905 [or 1904 or 1906 - probably 1905; writer refers to Jacob Smith's having one more year in law school - rec'd Bachelor's at CU in 1903], to FLC; some news of the Georges and GJR; encouragement and support for FLC. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, to FLC, Little Italy Neighborhood House, Brooklyn, Nov. 10, 1905, concerning recent [burglary] incidents at FLC's Brooklyn living quarters. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (3 pcs.) from Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Nov. 24, [ 1905 ?], concerning FLC's work among women and girls and her fears for her safety in a dangerous neighborhood. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Christmas note, 1905, Mrs. Miller to FLC, [always addressed as "M.G." - My Girl]. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Nov. 28, [ 1905 ?], re: boy thief referred to in other letters. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (2 pcs.) from Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Jan. 16, [ 1906 ?], re: FLC's recent experiences in Brooklyn and the great responsibility she must bear alone; thinks she might be better off at Hull House. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter (2 pcs.) from Mrs. Miller to FLC, Peterboro, Feb. 15, 1906, admonishing her to rest; praises her for past work. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Letter from Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Feb. 18, 1906, re: F's work; changes W.R. George has made in GJR Library; her son, Gerrit, Jr.'s plans for year's work in British Museum. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, June 20, 1906, to FLC, at Rochester, personal news; rather amusing comment on Upton Sinclair's The Jungle. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, May 19, 1910, brief personal note. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Feb. 7, ____, re: some work of Santayana's FLC has been reading. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, Peterboro, Sept. 19, _____, note of encouragement. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Mrs. Miller, n.d. [late Dec. or early Jan.], visit from Jacob Smith, etc. (Box 51, Folder 1)
- Other mss. items
  - FLC's reminiscences entitled "Initiation" with comment of donor: "Accurate story from the Geo. Jr. Republic Feb. 1899." Written ca. 1945. Concerns attempt to foil rendezvous. 5 pp. typescript. (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Diary notes, Aug. 1898-Mar. 1900, entitled "Stories from the George Junior Republic"; chiefly concerned with a twelve-year-old boy called Roxy and her attempts to befriend him, but also mention others. (12 pcs.) (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Three small notebooks containing:
    - Roster of 183 Citizens, 1896-1899, giving age, date child came and date he or she left, address. Not complete for some. (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Record of remarks made in "Court" by Arthur Anderson, Judge, Nov.-Dec. 1899, and in "Town Meeting," Jan. [1900?]. (Box 51, Folder 1)
    - Additional remarks of Anderson, Jan. 1900 -. (Box 51, Folder 1)
- Miscellanea
  - One snapshot of John Lincoln Miller studying ants. [Susan Dixwell Miller's grandson?] Small boy in frock and sunbonnet!! (Box 51, Folder 1)
  - Printed copy of NY Times editorial, "Half Century of the Republic," appearing in July 13, 1946 issue. Pasted on this sheet is clipping re: Dec. 1954 GJR fund drive, from NY Times. (Box 51, Folder 1)